<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Terms of accomodation, between those of the Episcopall, and their brethren of the Presbyterian perswasions supposed to be consistent with the declared principles of the most moderate of both parties, and humbly presented to the consideration of His Majesty, and both Houses of Parliament / by a countrey minister, a friend to Bath ...</title>
            <author>Countrey minister.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11939783</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11939783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51258</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51258)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 517:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Terms of accomodation, between those of the Episcopall, and their brethren of the Presbyterian perswasions supposed to be consistent with the declared principles of the most moderate of both parties, and humbly presented to the consideration of His Majesty, and both Houses of Parliament / by a countrey minister, a friend to Bath ...</title>
                  <author>Countrey minister.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Nevil ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterian Church --  Relations --  Church of England.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Relations --  Presbyterian Church.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51258:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51258:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>TERMS OF ACCOMMODATION,</hi> Between thoſe of the EPISCOPALL, And their Brethren of the PRESBYTERIAN PERSWASIONS.</p>
            <p>Suppoſed to be Conſiſtent with the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Principles</hi> of the moſt moderate of <hi>both Parties:</hi> And humbly preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Conſideration of his <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> and both <hi>Houſes of PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a <hi>Countrey Miniſter,</hi> a <hi>Friend</hi> to <hi>Both,</hi> a <hi>Stickler</hi> for <hi>Neither,</hi> but a <hi>Zealot</hi> for the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BEATI PACIFICI.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Nevil,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the ſign of the Plow in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51258:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51258:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Terms of Accommodation,</hi> BETWEEN Thoſe of the <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> and their Brethren of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt,</hi> I take for granted theſe <hi>Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata,</hi> or ſuppoſitions following (at leaſt until they be upon rational evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence diſproved by either Party) which I lay as a <hi>foundation</hi> to my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all <hi>differences</hi> in the Church, (except ſuch as ſtrike at the <hi>vitals</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the very <hi>being</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi>) are, with more agreeablenſs to principles of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and right <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and with more likelyhood of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manency,</hi> and <hi>ſtability,</hi> to be compoſed by <hi>accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then <hi>ſuppreſſion</hi> of diſſenting Parties.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in <hi>accommodation</hi> there muſt be a <hi>mutual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention</hi> of the Parties accommodating, upon ſuch
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51258:3"/>
               <hi>Conditions,</hi> as may afford both a <hi>ſaving Bargain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That in <hi>Religious Differences,</hi> ſuch an <hi>accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> cannot be made without a <hi>Salvo</hi> to the <hi>Conſcientious Principles</hi> of <hi>both Parties;</hi> neither of which can ſave, when their Conſciences loſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That (in the Caſe in hand) both the <hi>Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> (differing in no fundamental before-mentioned) are diſſenters <hi>capable</hi> of being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>accommodation;</hi> and ſeeing they do, upon plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible grounds, and ſuch as (in charity we are bound to believe) do really influence their Conſciences, juſtifie their ſeveral pretenſions, ought to be accommodated with allowance to both their conſcientious Principles.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That (to omit the ſeveral <hi>particular Tenets</hi> on both ſides, and their <hi>particular Pleas</hi> for them) in <hi>general,</hi> their <hi>reſpective Pleas</hi> may be thus ſtated.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The <hi>Epiſcoparian</hi> pleads (as his grand <hi>Principles</hi> ſwaying his <hi>Conſcience</hi>)
<list>
                     <item>1 (Not baulking <hi>Scripture</hi>) the harmonious <hi>conſent of Antiquity,</hi> as the beſt <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon the Records</hi> of Church affairs mentioned in <hi>Scripture.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 The <hi>Conſtitutions of this Church,</hi> conformable to the <hi>Law of the Land.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 The <hi>Presbyterian</hi> pleads (as the grand <hi>Principles</hi> ſwaying his <hi>Conſcience</hi>)
<list>
                     <item>1 (Not baulking <hi>Antiquity</hi>) the <hi>Letter of the Scripture,</hi> to which all <hi>Antiquity</hi> muſt be reduced, and judged by it.</item>
                     <item>2 The <hi>Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="6">6. That if what is here ſuppoſed rational to be yielded by the <hi>Epiſcoparian,</hi> be neither contrary to the <hi>current of Antiquity,</hi> or <hi>Scripture,</hi> nor repugnant to the legal <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51258:3"/>of this Church:</hi> And what is expected from the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> be neither evidently contrary to the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> nor aliene from <hi>Antiquity,</hi> nor repugnant to the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> all their pleas from <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Conſcience,</hi> for keeping up their mutual diſtance, are out of doors.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the <hi>plea</hi> of the <hi>Epiſcopal Party</hi> from the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Church,</hi> is of ſuch a nature, as may, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where it is not in conjunction with the former, (the ſtream of <hi>Antiquity</hi> commenting upon <hi>Scripture</hi>) be voided at their own pleaſures, the power of altering thoſe Conſtitutions (except where ſo backed as beforeſaid) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by <hi>Law</hi> in the hands of the preſent <hi>Governors</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> that is <hi>themſelves,</hi> and ſo can oblige them no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they <hi>will</hi> be obliged.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That the <hi>Plea</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party from the <hi>Covenant,</hi> obligeth them no farther in point of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> then it ſtands in <hi>conjunction with the word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches,</hi> and (by conſequence) that they may, <hi>ſalvâ Conſcientiâ,</hi> ſubmit to any Terms of accommodation, which are not repugnant to them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That (in effect) the limitations of the <hi>reformation</hi> engaged for in the <hi>Covenant;</hi> to the <hi>word of God,</hi> and the <hi>example of the beſt reformed Churches,</hi> are coincident. For how can it be judged, what <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>better</hi> or <hi>worſe reformed,</hi> but by the <hi>word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. That if the <hi>example of the beſt reformed Churches,</hi> be inſiſted upon as a <hi>Diſtinct</hi> limitation: yet, it being not expreſſed in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> what particular Churches the impoſers of the Covenant judged <hi>moſt Reformed,</hi> nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated what <hi>notion of Reformation</hi> it is, from whence they inſinuate ſome Churches to be <hi>more,</hi> and ſome <hi>leſs Reformed,</hi> (whether that which relates barely to the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from Rome,</hi> or that which relates to the <hi>degrees</hi> of pretended improvement of <hi>one Proteſtant Church</hi> beyond <hi>another,</hi> in point of reformation, though they all ſtand equally diſtant from <hi>Rome</hi>) it follows, that it is at the <hi>choice</hi> of the <hi>Covenanters</hi> to modell their <hi>reformation</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51258:4"/>to <hi>which notion</hi> they pleaſe: or rather, that it is their duty to <hi>reform</hi> according to that which <hi>any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church</hi> hath attained to, beyond the <hi>reſt,</hi> not eſpouſing the <hi>whole</hi> frame and conſtitution of <hi>any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church</hi> in groſs as their example, but picking that which ſeems moſt agreeable to Scripture, Antiquity, and right Reaſon out of <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. That, ſuppoſing a <hi>reduction of Epiſcopacy</hi> to the <hi>Terms</hi> hereafter ſpecified, it doth actually ceaſe to be <hi>that Prelacy</hi> which is abjured in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and (in effect) falls in with a <hi>Scriptural Presbyterie;</hi> and (by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) relaxeth the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the <hi>Covenanter</hi> to a liberty of fair compliance with it.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That however, (ſeeing the <hi>Covenant</hi> limits the endeavours of the <hi>Covenanter</hi> in this, aſwell as other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, to his <hi>place and calling;</hi> and reſerves the rights of Supream Authority in <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> which muſt be underſtood with reference to matters <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> as well as <hi>Civil</hi>) no <hi>private</hi> perſon or perſons can be obliged to reform againſt the will of that <hi>Authority,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an apparent exceeding the duty of their <hi>places and Callings:</hi> and (by conſequence) that it is the duty of every <hi>Covenanter,</hi> to endeavour by humble applications to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to procure the beſt Terms that he can for the reformation of the Church, and when he hath done his utmoſt that way, he is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded in that obligation, by a <hi>moral impoſsibility,</hi> being not in a capacity lawfully to act any further; except it be thought further incumbent upon him to make a <hi>poſitive,</hi> or (at leaſt) <hi>negative ſeparation</hi> from the <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe not conſtituted as he deſires: which principle, how far it comes under the condemnation of <hi>Schiſm</hi> (abjured in the <hi>ſame Article,</hi> as deeply as <hi>Prelacy</hi>) will admit a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Queſtion;</hi> and in the deciſion of it, muſt needs touch cloſe upon the ſtate of the Queſtion between the <hi>Papiſts</hi> on the <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>Browniſts</hi> on the <hi>other</hi> ſide, and <hi>us</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the juſtifiableneſs of the <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> in its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution before theſe times, and ſo cannot ſafely be moved by any true <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51258:4"/>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly</hi> upon theſe <hi>Poſtulata,</hi> if granted, I aſſert, [1.]<note place="margin">1. <hi>Aſſertions</hi> relating to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Epiſcopal Party.</hi>
               </note> That the <hi>Epiſcoparian</hi> party may with <hi>ſafety of Conſcience</hi> conſent to the <hi>Reduction of Epiſcopacy</hi> to the Modell of his <hi>Majeſties declaration concerning Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Affairs,</hi> ſeeing it is demonſtrable, that wherein that modell varies from the <hi>former <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſages</hi> of Epiſcopacy in this Nation, it comes nearer to the practice of <hi>Pure Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> For,</p>
            <list>
               <item>(1.) That the <hi>antient Biſhops</hi> were <hi>conſtant Preachers,</hi> appears by their <hi>Homilies,</hi> yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</item>
               <item>(2.) That they had their <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> which in his <hi>Majeſties modell</hi> are <hi>Suffragan Biſhops,</hi> is evident by many Teſtimonies produced in this caſe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the higheſt <hi>Epiſcoparians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(3.) That they had a <hi>Colledge of Presbyters</hi> who joined with them in all acts of <hi>Ordination,</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> is clear by the mention of πρεσβυτέριον in the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. in the work of <hi>impoſition of hands;</hi> and the frequent conjunction of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and his πρεσβυτέριον in <hi>Ignatius</hi> the great <hi>Patron of Epiſcopacy,</hi> in thoſe clauſes where he requires ſubjection from the people to Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Juriſdiction; of which many inſtances beſides theſe might be produced. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ad Epheſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ad Magneſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ad Philad. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ad Trall. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ad Smyrn. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(4.) That they <hi>delegated their power</hi> to any <hi>other perſons</hi> to act in their names, ſeems moſt improbable. Nay there is a paſſage in <hi>Ignatius,</hi> which not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely intimates, that (even in the neceſſary ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51258:5"/>of the <hi>Biſhop</hi>) his ſeat was <hi>void,</hi> or ſupplyed (which is moſt probable) by none or the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie alone.</hi> For he ſends commendations to his <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> when he was upon his Journey to <hi>Rome,</hi> with this clauſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>That he had left them under the only Epiſcopal inſpection of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> [Ign. ep. ad. <hi>Romanos.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(5.) That if ſuch <hi>delegation</hi> be ſuppoſed agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>Primitive pattern,</hi> yet (to be ſure) there is not one footſtep of a <hi>Lay-Chancellor or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary,</hi> exerciſing <hi>Eccleſiaſtical jurisdiction</hi> in all <hi>Antiquity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(6.) That <hi>confirmation, admiſſion to,</hi> and <hi>ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from the <hi>Lords Supper, Catechiſing</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing</hi> of <hi>Parochial differences,</hi> are works in which the <hi>Paſtors of particular Churches</hi> are moſt dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly concerned, and therefore are moſt rationally to be <hi>joyned with the Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyterie</hi> in all ſuch acts as concern them; may be concluded not repugnant to <hi>beſt Antiquity,</hi> till the perſon that queſtions <hi>it,</hi> ſhew ſufficient evidence from it for a Contrary practice then we have yet ſeen.</item>
               <item>(7.) And Laſtly, that <hi>Biſhops</hi> did not in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times act <hi>arbitrarily,</hi> but according to <hi>rule,</hi> the acknowleged <hi>antient Canons</hi> (among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> (at leaſt) whom we have now to do withall) evidence.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All which are the ſubſtance of the <hi>plat-form</hi> laid by his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and much conſonant to the <hi>model</hi> contrived by his <hi>Royal Father,</hi> whoſe knowledge in the nature of <hi>Primitive Epiſcopacy</hi> no man can doubt, who hath read his <hi>learned diſcourſes</hi> upon that ſubject; and thoſe appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by moſt <hi>Epiſcopal men,</hi> then in being: ſo that I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my aſſertion firm thus farr, at leaſt.</p>
            <p>But (2.) The <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> party may (<hi>ſalvâ conſcientiâ</hi>) condeſcend in theſe farther particulars upon their own Principles.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51258:5"/>
            <p n="1">(1.) To the <hi>reformation</hi> of <hi>Deans, Chapters,</hi> and <hi>Cathedral dependants</hi> in this manner or the like, as ſhall ſeem moſt adviſeable to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By annexing to every <hi>Cathedral dignity</hi> a <hi>Cure of ſouls,</hi> in, or near the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the <hi>Dioceſs</hi> where the <hi>Cathedral</hi> is, (eſpecially where the <hi>Legal main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> of a Church is moſt <hi>inconſiderable,</hi> and moſt of all, where it is <hi>impropriate</hi> to the <hi>Cathedral</hi> uſe:) and this Cure to be diſcharged by the <hi>Dignitary</hi> in <hi>perſon,</hi> except in caſe of neceſſary hinderance. It being apparent, that whatever footſteps of ſuch a <hi>Collegiate Society</hi> of <hi>Deans</hi> and <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> are to be found in <hi>Antiquity,</hi> inform us that the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of them was from the convenient ſituation of the <hi>Neighbouring Paſtors</hi> to the <hi>Epiſcopal ſeat</hi> to aſſiſt the <hi>Biſhop</hi> upon all occaſions, without damage to their flocks, when thoſe that lived at remoter diſtance could not be called in as often as he needed them without inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By erecting a <hi>ſtanding Presbytery,</hi> conſiſting of ſuch <hi>Miniſters,</hi> having <hi>Cure of Souls</hi> within or near the place of the <hi>Biſhops reſidence,</hi> at the choice of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the Miniſtry of the Dioceſs (the <hi>Dignitaries</hi> of the <hi>Cathedral</hi> not being included in the number, except ſo choſen) for the Conſtant aſiſtance of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> in <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary acts of juriſdiction</hi> which require not, or in ſuch <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary,</hi> as will not permit the <hi>delay</hi> requiſite to the orderly ſummoning of <hi>remoter Presbyters:</hi> There being no clear footſtep in <hi>Antiquity</hi> for the conſtitution of a <hi>ſelect ſociety of Presbyters</hi> to aſſiſt the <hi>Biſhop</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively to the reſt of their brethen) who are bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entituled to that <hi>Dignity</hi> by being entituled to a <hi>revenue</hi> annexed to the <hi>Mother Church;</hi> a relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which till about <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time (at leaſt) had no being.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By levelling all ſuch <hi>priviledges</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities</hi> as hinder the <hi>reformation</hi> of <hi>Cathedral depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,</hi> and rendring them obnoxious to the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51258:6"/>with the officers and members of <hi>Parochial Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. By taking away <hi>pluralities</hi> of ſuch <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal dignities,</hi> which hinder the <hi>Dignitaries</hi> from attending the Services, which their original foundation had reſpect unto.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By reducing the <hi>vaſt revenues</hi> of ſome <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks</hi> to a more <hi>moderate</hi> proportion, and aſſigning the <hi>ſurpluſſage</hi> of them, as an addition to the maintenance of <hi>Suffragan Biſhops,</hi> and for the bearing of the <hi>incidental charges</hi> of ſuch as are fain to attend the <hi>affairs of the Church</hi> upon occaſionall calls far from their homes to <hi>Synods</hi> or other <hi>Church Conventions;</hi> and other ſuch uſes. It being apparent, that till <hi>Cathedral Churches</hi> were <hi>built,</hi> they could not be <hi>endowed,</hi> or <hi>priviledged,</hi> and (by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence) that in the three laſt particulars, to plead Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Antiquity againſt what is propounded, involves a ſelf-contradiction.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) They may alſo, upon their <hi>own Principles,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to a <hi>Law</hi> for the <hi>ratifying of Ordination</hi> in theſe late years conferred by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> without exacting a Submiſſion to <hi>re-ordination</hi> in thoſe who Scruple it. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Biſhops hands</hi> are neceſſary to <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Cades</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of the Church of <hi>England</hi> p. 311.</note> otherwiſe then upon the account of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical conſtitution</hi> for <hi>orders</hi> ſake, will be hard to evidence from <hi>Scripture</hi> or pure <hi>Antiquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>Ordaining of Presbyters</hi> by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> licence, (as in the caſe of the antient <hi>Chorepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi</hi>) and in the neceſſary abſence, or want of Biſhops (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> teſtifie concerning the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and particularly at <hi>Alexandria</hi>) hath been of <hi>great Antiquity</hi> in the Church: and certainly if leave or abſence of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> render it lawful for <hi>Presbyters alone</hi> to <hi>ordain,</hi> it will follow that there is a <hi>radical</hi> and <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental power of Ordination</hi> in <hi>Presbyters,</hi> for elſe a <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> leave or <hi>abſence</hi> might as well impower a <hi>meer Laick</hi> to give orders, which was only reſtrained <hi>for Orders ſake,</hi> as was ſaid before.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51258:6"/>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>Arch. B. Bancroft</hi> and the reſt of his Brethren, who admitted the <hi>Scottiſh Biſhops</hi> to conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, required not their <hi>re-ordination:</hi> and ſurely they were not ignorant of what <hi>plea's</hi> lay againſt it from <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That in the Judgement of <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> late learned <hi>Prelates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pr. of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh, Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and it is ſaid, <hi>Morton.</hi>
               </note> the greateſt, if not only, blame with which <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall Ordination</hi> can be charged in <hi>England,</hi> is, that it was done <hi>ſchiſmatically.</hi> But it will be very hard to prove, that (according to the ſenſe of <hi>Antiquity</hi>) <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> is <hi>eo nomine</hi> null, becauſe performed by perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Schiſme.</hi> Nay our own <hi>Maſon de Miniſt. Augl.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>validity of Ordination</hi> of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> by <hi>F. Maſon.</hi>
               </note> proves that <hi>Schiſme in the Conſecrator doth not null the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of Biſhops,</hi> out of Antiquity; and (though he be no friend to <hi>Ordination</hi> by meer <hi>Presbyters</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> though he juſtifie it in <hi>forraign Churches,</hi> yet) there is <hi>par ratio</hi> in both, as to this caſe, I mean ſciſmatical conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Biſhops, and ordination of Presbyters.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) They may alſo, without wrong to their <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> give conſent to a more <hi>regular election and equall conſtitution</hi> of <hi>Synods,</hi> which with the impreſs of <hi>Soveraign Authority</hi> are the ordinary Legal original of Church-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and thoſe in whom (by repreſentation, as the whole <hi>body of the People</hi> in an <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi>) the whole <hi>body of the Clergy</hi> do chooſe the <hi>Laws</hi> they will be governed by. And under this head, it is ſuppoſed, No cogent reaſon from <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Antiquity</hi> can be given, why they may not conſent to theſe <hi>regulations</hi> following, or the like.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all <hi>members of Convocation</hi> (except the <hi>Biſhop</hi> himſelf, whoſe claime by vertue of his office is not denyed to be of great <hi>Antiquity,</hi> if the authority of <hi>antient Councils</hi> be allowed) being but <hi>Presbyters,</hi> may ſubmit to an <hi>equal election</hi> with the <hi>Clerks of Convocation</hi> except (which I think cannot be proved) there be any footſteps in pure <hi>Antiquity</hi> priviledging <hi>one</hi> Presbyter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>another</hi> without election to ſit in a Synod, and make Laws for the Church.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51258:7"/>
            <p n="2">2. That if <hi>Cathedral members</hi> ſit as repreſenters of <hi>diſtinct Collegiate bodies</hi> they belong to; either the number of them be leſſened, or the number of <hi>Clerks Elective</hi> be augmented to overballance them; it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unequal, that the <hi>Clerks</hi> who repreſent the <hi>whole Clergy,</hi> ſhould be lyable to be outvoted by the number of thoſe, who, whatever burthens they lay upon their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and the Churches under them, are by the <hi>priviledge of their ſociety</hi> little concerned in them themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That ſeeing the late diſſolution of Government hath expoſed us to ſo many <hi>Schiſms</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>factions</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> and the animoſities occaſioned by them are yet too flagrant among us; ſo that it may rationally be ſuppoſed, our mutual heats may hinder us from all recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation by the debates and concluſions of a <hi>Synod</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted <hi>of meer Natives;</hi> there be ſome courſe taken (as in the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Dort</hi>) to call in the aſſiſtance of ſome <hi>forraigne Reformed Divines,</hi> by way of <hi>advice,</hi> not <hi>juriſdiction;</hi> who being unintereſted in our quarrels, may be able to ſuggeſt better expedients for our <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation,</hi> then our paſſion and prejudice will ſuffer us to light on our ſelves. This <hi>propoſal</hi> is bottomed upon the uſe the <hi>antients</hi> made of <hi>General Councils,</hi> which ſeeing we cannot now have, it ſeems but equal, that when <hi>like cauſes</hi> call for <hi>forraigne advice,</hi> the ſame <hi>courſe</hi> be followed as near as it may.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That canvaſing for voices by <hi>Apparitors,</hi> &amp;c. be forbidden, and the preſent way of <hi>ſummoning Miniſters</hi> to ſuch <hi>election</hi> by <hi>Apparitors</hi> which gives them advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſo to do, and opportunity to leave thoſe unſummoned whoſe votes they doubt of, may be changed into a publike <hi>proclamation in all Market Towns,</hi> or the like, as ſhall ſeem beſt to Authority.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That no <hi>Proxie votes</hi> be admitted, except upon <hi>oath</hi> made, that the perſons <hi>deputing</hi> their <hi>Proxies</hi> are hindred from giving their attendance by ſome neceſſary impediment.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That all <hi>elections</hi> be made upon ſuch <hi>days</hi> as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51258:7"/>may not neceſſitate the Miniſters that live at diſtance to an inconvenience in reference to their <hi>Lords day la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours:</hi> and in ſuch <hi>places</hi> as are near the <hi>Center</hi> of every <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> that <hi>Miniſters</hi> from all parts may attend them with leſs inconvenience.</p>
            <p>Theſe laſt-mentioned particulars carry ſo much <hi>equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in the front of them, that it is not to be ſuppoſed, any one will think it needful to appeal to the practice of the <hi>antient Church</hi> concerning them: or if they ſhould, it were no difficult matter to derive ſufficient countenance for them from the records of <hi>antient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cills.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Nor is there any thing to ſcruple their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> in the granting it, from <hi>Scripture,</hi> or pure <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity,</hi> but rather much to induce them thereunto, in caſe it be farther deſired, That an <hi>abſtract</hi> be made of all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Laws</hi> in force, and publiſhed, that all men may know when they are, or are not obnoxious to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures:</hi> and thoſe litigations occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the diſperſion of them in <hi>ſo many Books</hi> (too many already, but likely to be <hi>vaſtly multiplyed,</hi> in caſe the conceit of ſome <hi>great Church-men</hi> now in being, hold good, that a great part of the <hi>Canon Laws</hi> is ſtill in force) no more turn <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Iudicatories</hi> into <hi>Courts of Common Pleas.</hi> And that <hi>viſitation Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> upon which <hi>Church-wardens</hi> are ſworn to preſent, be confined both in number and quality to ſuch a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and nature, as they may ſafely ſwear to.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Nor will it, to any one that conſidereth how ſevere the <hi>antient diſcipline of the Church</hi> was, in caſes of <hi>Scandal,</hi> and how indulgent in matters of <hi>Scruple,</hi> be thought repugnant to their principles before mentioned, if they be deſired to make the yoke of Church cenſures heavier for <hi>Scandalous Non-conformiſts</hi> to the Laws of <hi>God,</hi> then <hi>ſcrupulous Non-conformiſts</hi> to the Laws of the <hi>Church,</hi> and take care that they be executed with a like difference.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Nor will it be a matter of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> if upon the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51258:8"/>preceding Conſideration, it be deſired, that <hi>bare non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in circumſtantialls,</hi> where it is not joyned with open <hi>contempt of authority,</hi> or an <hi>evident fomenting of Schiſme and Faction,</hi> may not expoſe a <hi>Miniſters ſtation</hi> and Livelyhood to ſuch hazards as formerly.</p>
            <p n="7">(7.) But rather, that the <hi>few Controverted Ceremonies</hi> be laid aſide altogether, that they may be no more a <hi>Shibboleth</hi> or note of diſtinction, between <hi>Miniſter</hi> and <hi>Miniſter:</hi> nor expoſe the moſt conſcientious perſons (who are the only perſons apt to ſcruple in ſuch caſes) a prey to <hi>malicious proſecutors,</hi> who are upon all occaſions apt to make the neglect of them an occaſion of diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eting thoſe <hi>Miniſters,</hi> whoſe doctrine diſquiets their luſts.</p>
            <p n="8">(8.) And ſeeing the <hi>ſtrict obſervation of the Lords day,</hi> in the performance of publike and private duties of religion, is found by experience to conduce very much to the promoting of <hi>knowledge and piety</hi> where it is ſo obſerved; and <hi>ignorance and licentiouſneſs</hi> where it is neglected; it is ſuppoſed they need not ſcruple, (though poſſibly not upon the ſame ground, which the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> plead (the <hi>morality of the day,</hi>) yet (at leaſt) by an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical conſtitution</hi>) to enjoin it. To be ſure, if <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Fathers,</hi> (as ſome think) be not ſo ſevere, as to require a totall abſtinence from ſecular imployment, and recreations on that day, yet there is nothing in them againſt the practice of ſuch an abſtinence in order to religious ends.</p>
            <p n="9">(9.) It is hardly to be imagined, that <hi>conſcience</hi> can find ſo much in <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Antiquity,</hi> for the Juſtification of the <hi>whole frame</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Liturgy,</hi> and the <hi>forms of Ordination,</hi> &amp;c. as that they ſhoold rationally conclude it a Sin to make any alterations of <hi>miſ-tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations</hi> or <hi>inconvenient expreſſions,</hi> the main body and bulke of them being preſerved, which few quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel at.</p>
            <p n="10">(10.) <hi>Laſtly,</hi> the multitude of <hi>holy-days</hi> (as they are called) yet remaining, is under the ſame diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51258:8"/>as to their foundation in pure Antiquity, and ſo may (even with ſafety to their <hi>principles</hi>) be leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened.</p>
            <p>I have not multiplyed all theſe heads, as if I thought it unpoſſible to accommodate the Presbyterians upon any <hi>eaſier Terms,</hi> or becauſe I think it neceſſary they ſhould inſiſt upon <hi>every punctillio</hi> of theſe <hi>Propoſals.</hi> Nay, <hi>ſome</hi> of them may poſſibly be already ſufficiently ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>in law</hi> for ought I know, (who confeſs my ſelf not much verſed in that kind of reading;) and ſo it may be ſuperfluous to deſire them. However, in caſe ſuch proviſion be <hi>already made,</hi> it were but meet, for ſatisfaction of thoſe who deſire it, that it be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <hi>where,</hi> and <hi>how</hi> that proviſion is <hi>made;</hi> and that aſſurance be given, that ſuch Laws ſhall be better execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the future then heretofore. And I have this charity for the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters,</hi> that I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded ſome very few additions to the <hi>model,</hi> and <hi>conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Kings Declaration,</hi> and thoſe barely uſefull to render them practicable; will reconcile the moſt of them to their Brethren, and render them moſt entirely one with them. And what pity would it be to caſt off ſo conſiderable a number <hi>of learned, orthodox, peaceable and powerful Preachers</hi> from publike imployment in the <hi>Church,</hi> for not complying in the utmoſt extremity to thoſe things, which may be more ſafely indulged by the <hi>profeſſed principles</hi> of their <hi>Governors,</hi> then they can be practiſed by <hi>theirs?</hi> And let it be ſeriouſly conſidered, whether if St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who dealt ſo moderately in the <hi>firſt Synod at Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> in a queſtion of as great or greater importance then any before mentioned, would, if they were now in <hi>England,</hi> not very much condemn the <hi>violent principles</hi> and actings of ſome perſons, who profeſs to <hi>ſucceed</hi> them. Surely if to <hi>become all things</hi> (lawfull) <hi>to all men that we may win ſome,</hi> be an <hi>Apoſtolical practice,</hi> and commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Scripture</hi> to our imitation as it is, that <hi>Principle</hi> that will not allow men to <hi>become any thing</hi> (though never
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51258:9"/>ſo lawful upon their own declared grounds) to ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a number of their <hi>conſcientious Brethren,</hi> is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commendable nor <hi>Apoſtolical.</hi> But it may be, the fault is on the <hi>other ſide.</hi> It is not meet the <hi>Epiſcoparian</hi> ſhould <hi>(become all things)</hi> to them, and they comply in <hi>nothing</hi> with them again. Very true; it is not. And therefore, in the next place, upon the former <hi>poſtulata,</hi> as they refer to the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party, I proceed to <hi>Aſſert,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Aſſertions</hi> relating to the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Party.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> may <hi>(ſalvâ conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiâ).</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">[1.] (In reference to <hi>Church-Government.</hi>)</p>
            <p n="1">1. Admit (at leaſt <hi>Jure humano,</hi> as an Officer of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> conſtitution, or as deputed by the <hi>Kings Majeſty,</hi> and by vertue of his acknowledged <hi>Supremacy</hi>) a <hi>ſingle Perſon</hi> to preſide over the <hi>Presbyterie,</hi> of ſuch or ſuch a convenient Precinct, as a <hi>Maſter of a Colledge</hi> over his <hi>Fellows.</hi> For though the <hi>Scripture</hi> do not (according to their grounds) <hi>appoint</hi> any ſuch Officer, yet it doth not <hi>forbid</hi> the Conſtitution of ſuch an one by the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> for more regular managery of affairs: and it is doubtfull (at leaſt) whether ſuch an one were not admitted into the Church (for the <hi>remedy of Schiſme</hi>) as <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith, before the death of St. <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It need not ſcruple their <hi>Conſciences</hi> by what <hi>name</hi> (ſo it be a name of honour and reverence) he be called; whether <hi>Father,</hi> or <hi>Preſident,</hi> or <hi>Moderator,</hi> or <hi>Super-intendent,</hi> or <hi>Biſhop.</hi> And if the Favour of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to this <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Title,</hi> add another of <hi>Civil Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> I know not but they may without ſcruple call him by that Name; as when an <hi>Earldom</hi> (as lately it fell out in <hi>England,</hi> in a <hi>Noble Family</hi>) devolves upon a <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel,</hi> I think, <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> and <hi>Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> doth nevertheleſs belong to him, becauſe he is a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</hi> It appears not to me, but the lawfulneſs of the Titles of <hi>Maſter,</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> given to <hi>Miniſters,</hi> is as diſputable from the Scripture, as that of <hi>My Lord.</hi> Though it little becomes Miniſters to ſtrive for them, or be offended with thoſe that ſcruple to give them.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51258:9"/>
            <p n="3">3. Nor need it be a <hi>ſcruple of Conſcience,</hi> that ſuch a perſon is continued in his <hi>Chair</hi> for <hi>Term of life,</hi> or <hi>quamdiu bene ſe geſſerit,</hi> and is not choſe anew, on every occaſion of publick meeting. For in this the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> I think (as to any poſitive determination) is deeply ſilent, and <hi>Antiquity</hi> favours not the <hi>later</hi> conſtitution at all, as far as I underſtand.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If this <hi>Perſon</hi> have large and ample <hi>Revenues</hi> beyond his Brethren, allowed him, ſuitable to a <hi>Governor</hi> deputed by <hi>Authority,</hi> and to maintain the <hi>dignity of his place,</hi> &amp;c. (though it be true, that <hi>too large Incomes</hi> to Officers of the Church, are but <hi>baits of Ambition,</hi> and <hi>temptations to ſupercilious Lording</hi> and domineering over the Flock) I think need not ſcare the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of any man from <hi>accommodation;</hi> ſeeing <hi>Scripture</hi> determines not the <hi>exact proportion</hi> of Maintenance which the <hi>Governors of the Church</hi> may require, and <hi>no more!</hi> and (if a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and leading man of that ſide which goes for <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. <hi>B.</hi> on the <hi>Worceſt.</hi> Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> ſay true) ſo large ſumms in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time, and <hi>Farms and Lands, were at the Biſhops diſpoſall, that ſome of them complained of the burthen of managing them.</hi> And how much they allowed themſelves, or the Church allowed them out of thoſe vaſt ſumms, who can tell?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Nor doth the Conſtitution of <hi>Deans and Chapters,</hi> nor their <hi>Revenues</hi> (as they are a kind of <hi>Collegiate preferments,</hi> for the encouragement of <hi>eminent Divines,</hi> and in caſe they were ſo modelled as their influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence might be leſs in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical affairs,</hi> farther then they are elected by the <hi>Clergy, ut ſuprà</hi>) offer any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the forementioned <hi>Principles</hi> of a <hi>Presbyterian Conſcience;</hi> For neither <hi>Scripture, Antiquity,</hi> nor <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> forbid or exclude ſuch <hi>Societies</hi> or their <hi>Endowments,</hi> under that notion. Yea in the late times, when ſome of <hi>thoſe in power</hi> ſtiffly pleaded the <hi>Covenant for extirpation</hi> of them, to juſtifie <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> the <hi>Dean and Prebends of Chriſts Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> would not be perſwaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve themſelves concerned in that <hi>Article,</hi> becauſe they ſtood barely in a <hi>Collegiate Capacity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51258:10"/>
            <p n="6">6. Nor is it a <hi>matter of Conſcience</hi> to thoſe of that judgement, who are not <hi>Ordained already,</hi> to ſubmit to <hi>Epiſcopal Ordination,</hi> whiles they admit a competent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Presbyters</hi> to lay on hands with them. Nay <hi>ſome</hi> of them (it ſeems) are ſo far ſatisfied in it, that ſeeing the <hi>Law</hi> requires it of them, and divers of their people <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copally</hi> minded, ſcruple the <hi>lawfulneſs of their adminſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> without it, they do ſubmit to ſuper-induce it upon their <hi>former Ordination;</hi> Nor need any one of <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Principles,</hi> refuſe the impoſition of <hi>Epiſcopal hands,</hi> becauſe the Scripture ſeems to inveſt a <hi>Presbyterie</hi> with it. For <hi>Biſhop</hi> includes <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and he, (being not only a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> but a <hi>Presbyter</hi>) with his aſſiſtants, make a <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The want of <hi>ruling Elders,</hi> which have been pleaded for as neceſſary Officers of the Church, need not ſtick with their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> if the <hi>Church-Wardens</hi> were well choſen annually, and conſcientious in their offices, and encouraged by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſo to be. For who ſees not that (<hi>mutato nomine</hi>) a <hi>Church-Warden</hi> is a plain <hi>Lay-Elder,</hi> as the <hi>Over-ſeer of the poor</hi> is a <hi>Scripture-Deacon,</hi> (at leaſt as to <hi>one</hi> part of his office, if the <hi>Epiſcoparian</hi> be not ſatisfied that that is all) and <hi>annual,</hi> or <hi>not annual,</hi> where Scripture is ſilent in determining, ſhould make no difference,</p>
            <p n="8">8. Nor need they be diſturbed upon a <hi>Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious account,</hi> if (while <hi>acts of Juriſdiction</hi> run in his name, with the expreſs <hi>conſent</hi> of his <hi>Clergy or Presbyterie</hi>) ſuch as meerly relate to <hi>matter of Order,</hi> ſuppoſe the <hi>tacite conſent of the Presbyterie,</hi> and (for expedition ſake, and eaſe to the Miniſters aſſiſtant to him, whoſe occaſions would be too much intrenched upon, if in every ſuch matter they ſhould be Convened) run in the <hi>Biſhops name only:</hi> For ſuch a power muſt be placed ſomewhere, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Intervals</hi> of <hi>Presbyterian Aſſemblies,</hi> even where they are ſettled moſt to the mind of the <hi>Patrons of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie;</hi> and comes under the rule of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that <hi>all things be done decently and in order.</hi> And if any, <hi>(extra
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51258:10"/>Conſeſſum Presbyterorum)</hi> why not in the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> as well as any <hi>other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. That ſome <hi>under-Officers,</hi> as <hi>Notaries</hi> and <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> &amp;c. neceſſary for the carrying on of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> be allowed, is ſo far from claſhing with <hi>Presbyterian Principles,</hi> that the only thing that they have cauſe to complain of herein, is that they are too often not ſo <hi>honeſt</hi> as they ſhould be; and that they are not maintained out of a <hi>publick purſe</hi> (rather then by <hi>occaſional fees</hi>) which were the more likely way to <hi>make</hi> and <hi>keep</hi> them ſo.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The <hi>Presbyterian Conſcience</hi> picks no quarrel at the juriſdiction which the Law placeth in the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and his <hi>Chancellors,</hi> and other <hi>Civilians</hi> acting under him in caſes of <hi>Teſtaments</hi> and <hi>Marriages,</hi> as being meerly <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumenta,</hi> things annexed to, and not properly parts of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">[2] In reference to <hi>Liturgy, habit of Miniſters, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies,</hi> and <hi>Feſtivals, Presbyterian Principles</hi> may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, as I ſuppoſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The lawfulneſs of an <hi>impoſed Form of Prayer (in Theſi)</hi> and the conveniency of it in reference to the <hi>eſſential parts</hi> of ſacred <hi>adminiſtrations;</hi> and <hi>(in Hypotheſi)</hi> the lawfulneſs and compleatneſs of the <hi>Form eſtabliſhed</hi> in this Church, in reference to ſuch <hi>Adminiſtrations,</hi> with very little alteration in any thing of moment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That divers <hi>other parts</hi> of the <hi>Service eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi> are very good, and edifying, and (with liberty to forbear <hi>ſome paſſages</hi> which are offenſive to their people, till they be amended) may be when required, prevailed with to uſe ſo much of it, as will declare them unwilling, upon this point, to break with their Brethren. For they know, that <hi>ſome</hi> forms have <hi>Scriptural warrant;</hi> and (therein) <hi>other</hi> forms a <hi>Scriptural precedent,</hi> and (upon that account) <hi>none</hi> unlawful, farther then they contain ſomething <hi>anti-Scriptural</hi> in their compoſition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are ſenſible, that it is the mind of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> that all Sacred Duties, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51258:11"/>in <hi>Solemn Aſſemblies,</hi> ſhould be performed with the greateſt <hi>reverence;</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> muſt be <hi>glorified with the body as well as the ſpirit;</hi> and therefore have only a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel at ſuch <hi>Ceremonies</hi> as are only enjoyned upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>ſignificancy,</hi> and do not <hi>naturally</hi> (as circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances requiſite to the <hi>Worſhip</hi> in hand) emerge from the <hi>quality</hi> thereof; for with ſuch as theſe, upon the grounds mentioned, they are perfectly friends.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They ſo well know, that an <hi>unlimited liberty of habits,</hi> gives a Temptation to <hi>Miniſters</hi> to cloath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>a la mode,</hi> and ſo, many times to conform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>common extravagancies</hi> of undecent <hi>faſhions,</hi> and thereby loſe that reputation of <hi>gravity</hi> which ſhould adorn the <hi>Miniſterial function</hi> in the eyes of the world, and therefore cannot but judge it agreeable to <hi>Scripture,</hi> that that liberty be reſtrained, by the enjoyning of grave and comely garments, and it is believed, they forbear ſome of thoſe enjoyned in the <hi>Canon</hi> it ſelf, not from a principle of <hi>faction</hi> and <hi>ſingularity,</hi> but only becauſe the long <hi>diſuſe</hi> of them, hath rendred them ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth in the eyes of their people, and they are unwilling to let others (who upon ſome accounts may do it with leſs offence) render them more <hi>familiar</hi> by their uſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they take them up: only they ſcruple the uſe of <hi>veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments peculiarly appropriated to divine Service,</hi> as thinking them proper to the <hi>old Law,</hi> and aboliſhed with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> they may (notwithſtanding their perſwaſion, that no power on earth can make any portion of time <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecally holy</hi>) admit the obſervation of thoſe eminent <hi>Feſtivals of the Church,</hi> that tend to the keeping in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance the <hi>Birth, Circumciſion, Baptiſm, Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Aſcenſion</hi> of our bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> and the <hi>deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> as they do other <hi>Anniverſary thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings,</hi> appointed by <hi>Publick Authority;</hi> ſo as no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation be declared to lie upon the Conſcience to obſerve them, from any <hi>peculiar holineſs</hi> in thoſe, more then in other dayes; and others aboliſhed or left indifferently to be obſerved or omitted.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51258:11"/>
            <p>I am very confident, that very <hi>few</hi> of that Party which they call <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> will find themſelves concerned in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to diſpute the lawfulneſs of <hi>many</hi> (if <hi>any</hi>) of the fore-mentioned <hi>Conceſſions</hi> (as here ſtated) in order to a <hi>friendly accommodation.</hi> And am alſo ſo charitable to thoſe of the ſoberer ſort of <hi>Epiſcoparians,</hi> as to think that upon a <hi>publike Declaration,</hi> that they can yield thus far, and intend not to ſtart <hi>new ſcruples,</hi> when theſe here mentioned are ſatisfied; (which I perceive is the <hi>jealouſie</hi> that contributes much to the continuing our diſtances, whiles the <hi>ruling Party</hi> are ſuſpitious that if once they begin to abate, the others for whoſe ſake they do it will grow unreaſonable in their demands, and think to make uſe of one Conceſſion, as an Argument to prevail for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>in infinitum</hi>) they would advance nearer towards them. And hereby (unqueſtionably) <hi>thoſe Brethren</hi> may, either expect to be <hi>gratified</hi> in their deſires, or render the <hi>perſons that deny them</hi> before God and the world, inexcuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, if they would generally agree on the Terms on which they will be ſatisfied, and ſolemnly declare that upon the Conceſſion of them, they will acquieſce, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſturbing the peace of the Church. And indeed it ſeems but reaſonable that this ſhould be required of them; that ſo <hi>their Governors</hi> may be aſſured that they have no <hi>reſerves in ambuſcado</hi> to diſturb them afreſh, when the <hi>main body</hi> of their ſcruples is <hi>disbanded</hi> and <hi>diſmiſſed the Field.</hi> And I have taken this pains of purpoſe, (not to preſcribe to the <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> of the <hi>one,</hi> or the <hi>other</hi> perſwaſion, my own conceptions as a juſt ſtandard or ballance by which the <hi>Articles of Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> muſt neceſſarily be meaſured or weighed out: but) <hi>partly,</hi> to excite them, by a kind of <hi>Pattern,</hi> how imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſoever, (drawn out of thoſe Notions which by Books or Diſcourſes I have taken up concerning the main differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences between them, and the Principles upon which they are engaged to maintain their contrary Aſſertions) to do ſomething more perfect themſelves of the like nature: And <hi>partly,</hi> with all ſubmiſſion and reverence, to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51258:12"/>thoſe in <hi>Publike Authority,</hi> if the <hi>Parties themſelves</hi> will not, in what way <hi>they</hi> may quickly put an end to theſe ſtrifes and diviſions; to wit, by requiring them ſeverally (each ſide for themſelves) to ſtate the utmoſt of their <hi>demands</hi> and <hi>deſires,</hi> and the utmoſt of the <hi>Conceſſions</hi> and <hi>Condeſcentions</hi> which they can with a <hi>ſafe Conſcience</hi> yield each other upon thoſe <hi>demands;</hi> together with the <hi>grounds</hi> upon which they can go <hi>no farther;</hi> taken from the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely owned Rules and Principles</hi> by which they will be tryed in Concernments of this Nature: and (upon the whole matter) make themſelves <hi>Judges</hi> in the caſe, and compound the difference ſo, as it may offer leaſt violence to thoſe <hi>Principles of Conſcience</hi> on either hand. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, what Perſons or Parties ſoever ſhall upon <hi>other Principles</hi> then thoſe of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or farther then thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> by which <hi>their Conſcience is governed</hi> do require, keep open our wounds, and obſtruct a <hi>Chriſtian and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Accommodation;</hi> will <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> declare themſelves guilty of a <hi>Schiſmatical Deſign</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> for ſome baſe and unworthy ends, and juſtly expoſe themſelves to the <hi>jealouſie of the Magiſtrate,</hi> as thoſe that nurſe a <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of new diſturbances</hi> to the State upon that account.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51258:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
